Edward J. Bartek Papers VHP2006/7
CCSU Veterans History Project
Edward J. Bartek Papers
Bulk, 1940-1944
1940-1944, 2006
VHP2006/7
CCSU Veterans History Project
36.0 Digital objects 1 interview DVD
This collection details Edward Bartek’s experiences in the Pacific during World War II. The collection contains video of oral history interview, journals, photographs. The materials provide information on various military engagements in the Pacific from Kiska to New South Wales. Along with evidence of U.S. military moral and courage the collection brings to light the impact of war related stress and isolation on military personnel.
Bartek, Edward J., 1921 - 2010
Biographical/Historical note
Edward Bartek enlisted in the United States Navy in 1939 to see the world. Receiving his basic training in Rhode Island he subsequently was assigned to the U.S.S. Quincy in Norfolk, Virginia. After seventeen days aboard the U.S.S. Quincy, Edward was transferred to the U.S.S. Ranger, an aircraft carrier which was sent to Guantanamo Bay for maneuvers. Edward served as an Electrician’s Mate aboard the U.S.S. Ranger as it patrolled the Atlantic in search of German submarines. After serving two and a half years on the U.S.S. Ranger Edward was assigned to the destroyer, the U.S.S. Beale as the Electrician’s Mate 1st Class. Supervising 13 other electricians on the U.S.S. Beale, Edward took part in eleven invasions, two sea battles, numerous air attacks, shore bombardments and convoys.
Conditions Governing Access note
Open for Research
Custodial History note
All manuscripts and photographs donated were digitized and digitally preserved. The donor retained all original manuscripts and photographs.
Online Access
An online exhibition of this veteran's papers can be accessed at project's website
Beale (Destroyer: DD471).; United States. Navy.; Aleutian Islands (Alaska); Degaussing; New Britain Island (Papua New Guinea); Philippines; Veterans -- United States -- Mental health; World War, 1939-1945; World War, 1939-1945 -- Campaigns -- Pacific Area; World War, 1939-1945 -- Naval operations; World War, 1939-1945 -- Personal narratives, American
- Series I: Personal Papers, VHP2006/7.I
  - Ship’s Diary: U.S.S. Ranger and U.S.S. Beale, April 1940 – Dec 1944; VHP2006/7.I.1; 15.0 pages
  - Diary: U.S.S. Beale, DD471 / Staten Island to Kiska to Cape Gloucester, Oct 23, 1942 – Nov 30, 1944; VHP2006/7.I.2; 60.0 pages
  - Synopsis of Oral History Interview with Edward J. Bartek, April 5, 2006; VHP2006/7.I.3
  - Painting of Cape Gloucester, New Guinea by Edward Bartek, n.d; VHP2006/7.I.4
- Series II: Publications, VHP2006/7.II
  - WW II Veteran participates in Oral History Project, May 3, 2006; VHP2006/7.II.1; 2.0 Digital objects
    General note
    Author Phyllis Royx reports on navy veteran Edward Bartek’s participation in Central Connecticut State University’s Oral History Project. The article discusses Edward’s childhood as a foster child and his subsequent success as teacher, author, and poet. The article originally appeared in The Reminder on May 3, 2006.
- Series III: Multi-Media, VHP2006/7.III
  - Subseries A: Still Images, VHP2006/7.III
    - Group of unidentified crew members on the deck of the U.S.S. Beale, between 1943 and 1944; VHP2006/7.III.1
    - Unidentified crew members posing on the deck of the U.S.S. Beale, between 1943 and 1944; VHP2006/7.III.2
    - Members of the U.S.S. Beale's electrical department, between 1943 and 1944; VHP2006/7.III.3
      Back row from left to right, unidentified sailor, Jim McKay, unidentified sailor, Walker, Paul Boehm, and unidentified sailor. Front row from left to right, unidentified sailor, Hamm, unidentified sailor with dog, Forrest Kistler, and Norris Rothchild
    - Five crew members posing on the deck of the U.S.S. Beale, between 1943 and 1944; VHP2006/7.III.4
    - Group of crew members posing on the deck of the U.S.S. Beale, between 1943 and 1944; VHP2006/7.III.5
    - U.S.S. Beale’s Machinists’ department posed on the deck with ships in the background, between 1943 and 1944; VHP2006/7.III.6
    - Crew members pose on the deck of the U.S.S. Beale, between 1943 and 1944; VHP2006/7.III.7
    - “Shooting line” Shooting a rope line to join the U.S.S. Beale with the U.S.S. Van Valkenburgh (DD-656), between 1943 and 1944; VHP2006/7.III.8
    - Delivery between two destroyers, the U.S.S. Beale and the U.S.S. Van Valkenburgh (DD-656), between 1943 and 1944; VHP2006/7.III.9
    - The U.S.S. Beale (right) gets oil from tanker (left), between 1943 and 1944; VHP2006/7.III.10
    - Sailors working together aboard the U.S.S. Beale, between 1943 and 1944; VHP2006/7.III.11
    - Destruction of an unidentified U.S. destroyer hit by kamikazes, Okinawa, Japan, between 1943 and 1944; VHP2006/7.III.12
    - U.S.S. Beale under fire by kamikazes, Okinawa, Japan, between 1943 and 1944; VHP2006/7.III.13
    - U.S. destroyers in the distance sinking after air attack by kamikazes, Okinawa, Japan, between 1943 and 1944; VHP2006/7.III.14
    - U.S.S. Beale sailors launching whale boat, between 1943 and 1944; VHP2006/7.III.15
    - U.S.S. Beale preparing for air attack, between 1943 and 1944; VHP2006/7.III.16
    - U.S.S. Beale under attack, between 1943 and 1944; VHP2006/7.III.17
    - U.S.S. Beale enduring rough seas, between 1943 and 1944; VHP2006/7.III.18
    - U.S. Fletcher class destroyer in the distance, seen from the U.S.S. Beale, between 1943 and 1944; VHP2006/7.III.19
    - U.S. Fletcher Class Destroyer in the near distance, seen from the U.S.S. Beale, between 1943 and 1944; VHP2006/7.III.20
    - Close up of a U.S. Fletcher Class destroyer, seen from the U.S.S. Beale, between 1943 and 1944; VHP2006/7.III.21
    - Ocean view from the bridge of the U.S.S. Beale, between 1943 and 1944; VHP2006/7.III.22
    - Sailors aboard the U.S.S. Beale performing depth charge practice, between 1943 and 1944; VHP2006/7.III.23
    - U.S.S. Beale crew members rescuing a man overboard, between 1943 and 1944; VHP2006/7.III.24
    - "Full speed ahead.” U.S.S. Beale traveling at 45 knots, between 1943 and 1944; VHP2006/7.III.25
    - View of ocean as the U.S.S. Beale moves at full speed, between 1943 and 1944; VHP2006/7.III.26
    - View of the U.S.S. Beale anchored, between 1943 and 1944; VHP2006/7.III.27
    - Edward J. Bartek in navy uniform on the streets of Sydney, Australia, between 1943 and 1944; VHP2006/7.III.28
    - Edward J. Bartek in shirt and sweater, VHP2006/7.III.29
    - Edward J. Bartek seated in chair, July 11,2006; VHP2006/7.III.30
  - Subseries B: Moving Images, VHP2006/7.IIIb
    - Oral History Interview with Edward J. Bartek, April 15, 2006; VHP2006/7.IIIb.1; Hurst, Eileen (Disk DVD VHP2006/7, Box VHP Interview 2006)